
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emacs TV</title>
    <link>https://emacs.tv</link>
    <atom:link href="https://emacs.tv/videos.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Emacs videos</description>
    <item>
      <title>GNU Emacs do Zero - Episódio 02</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NnrConrvGxg</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NnrConrvGxg</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NnrConrvGxg">youtube</a><br><br>Neste segundo episódio da série GNU Emacs do Zero, você vai compreender melhor como funciona o ELisp entre tantas outras teclas atalhos e edição com org-mode e org-agenda.

  Manual oficial do Elisp: https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/eintr/

  Curso completo de Emacs Lisp do @blauaraujocursos  https://youtu.be/5vSdG9n9c7c?si=CLiBFdH26Xggn2zu</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 01:13:30 +0000</pubDate><category>beginner</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creating an Emacs Package from Concept to MELPA (Part 1)</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l6o13pLo_Ms</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l6o13pLo_Ms</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l6o13pLo_Ms">youtube</a><br><br>In this series we will be developing the rare-words Emacs package, a package that highlights rare words in your Emacs buffer, and then trying to publish it to MELPA.</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 20:10:38 +0000</pubDate><category>elisp</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs lisp and gptel building custom llm tools to call emacs functions</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M386KUIh3Xc</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M386KUIh3Xc</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M386KUIh3Xc">youtube</a><br><br>Using Emacs with the gptel package we can create gpt-tools for llms that call emacs functions to provide the llm with information about our emacs set up

  i was thinking couldnt you write emacs gptel-tools for llms and did a quick search and came across the emacs-mcp mcp server which wasnt quite what i was after.

  so i refactored the code from the emacs-mcp package into the gptel-tool format for use with the gptel package and llms that support tool usage like llama and gemini

  i created a gptel-custom-tools.el file with 32 gptel-tools for emacs which can be loaded using the gptel use package code block

  the gptel-tools allow the llm to report the state of your emacs set up by listing installed packages, modes and variables. as well as reading the manuals and looking up docstrings for elisp symbols

  refactored from mpontus emacs-mcp package

  emacs-mcp
  https://github.com/mpontus/emacs-mcp

  gptel-custom-tools.el
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles/blob/master/.config/emacs/lisp/gptel-custom-tools.el

  early-init.el
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles/blob/master/.config/emacs/early-init.el

  init.el
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles/blob/master/.config/emacs/init.el

  ollama
  https://ollama.com/library/llama3.1
  https://ollama.com/library/llama3.2

  dotfiles org mode
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles/blob/master/nixos-dotfiles.org

  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles/blob/master/nixos-dotfiles.org#auth-source

  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles/blob/master/nixos-dotfiles.org#lisp-directory

  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles/blob/master/nixos-dotfiles.org#gptel-custom-toolsel</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 21:08:08 +0000</pubDate><category>ai</category>
<category>gptel</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI Augmented, Language Agnostic, SWE Workflow, in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kpExav29OjM</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kpExav29OjM</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kpExav29OjM">youtube</a><br><br>https://aider.chat/
  https://github.com/MatthewZMD/aidermacs
  https://opensource.com/article/18/8/what-how-makefile

  https://github.com/rajp152k/.dotfiles</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 09:30:37 +0000</pubDate><category>ai</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ancient Greek Tweaks in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oToTtoK1PQ0</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oToTtoK1PQ0</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oToTtoK1PQ0">youtube</a><br><br>How to get Ancient Greek to work flawlessly in Emacs
  https://github.com/emacselements/my-ancient-greek-tweaks
  https://github.com/emacselements/screenshot-ocr
  My website: https://emacselements.com/</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 08:50:36 +0000</pubDate><category>writing</category>
<category>greek</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ep712 Emacs Lisp, Move File to Parent Dir. car cdr cons, Supreme Functional Programing No Variable</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n_JUKfSf8sc</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n_JUKfSf8sc</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n_JUKfSf8sc">youtube</a><br><br>Video Summary (Generated by AI, Editedby Human.)

  In this video, Xah Lee codes in Emacs Lisp to create a command that moves files or marked files to their parent directory (0:08).

  Here's a breakdown of the video's content:

  • Demonstration of manual file movement in Emacs Dired (1:02): The speaker first demonstrates the manual process of moving files in Emacs's Dired mode, which involves splitting windows, navigating directories, marking files, and using the capital R key to move them (1:02-2:08).
  • He emphasizes the desire to automate this process with a single command (2:12).
  • Introduction to Dired and File Managers (3:28): The speaker explains Dired as Emacs's directory editor, which is essentially a file manager.
  • He compares it to Windows File Explorer, Mac Finder, and various Linux file managers (3:28-4:32).
  • Getting a list of marked files (5:02): The first step in coding the command is to get a list of files that are currently marked in Dired.
  • If no files are marked, the file under the cursor is considered the "current file" (5:02-6:10).
  • The dired-get-marked-files command is used for this purpose (7:21).
  • Finding the parent directory (9:25): The speaker then looks for the function to find the parent directory of a given file path.
  • He refers to his own Emacs Lisp tutorial for this (9:32-11:58).
  • He identifies file-name-directory as the function to get the directory of a file and later introduces file-name-parent-directory for obtaining the parent directory specifically (52:22).
  • Renaming/Moving files with rename-file (12:50): The rename-file command is introduced as the way to move or rename files, following Unix conventions (13:13).
  • Discussion on car and cdr in Lisp (15:22): A significant portion of the video is dedicated to explaining car and cdr (pronounced "car" and "carder" by the speaker) in Lisp.
  • Cons Cells: He explains that Lisp lists are fundamentally built from "cons cells," which are pairs of two things (17:45).
  • car refers to the first part of a cons cell, and cdr refers to the second part (20:16-20:58).
  • Nesting for Lists: Lists are formed by nesting these cons cells (21:56).
  • Historical Context: The speaker provides historical context, explaining that this design originated from early Lisp machines that had hardware optimized for these two-part cells (23:41).
  • Modern Alternatives: He advises against using the nested car and cdr functions (like cadr or cddar) for accessing elements in a list, calling them "idiotic" and "silly" (28:18-33:11).
  • Instead, he recommends using higher-level functions like nth for direct access (33:37) and push and pop for stack-like operations (36:56).
  • List Traversal and Efficiency: He highlights that functions like length for lists are inefficient because they have to traverse each element, which is a nature of Lisp's linked list implementation (38:55).
  • Completing the file movement command (42:30): The speaker proceeds to finalize the Emacs Lisp command, using mapc to apply the rename-file function to each selected file, concatenating the parent directory with the file's name (55:57).
  • Testing the command (56:30): The command is successfully tested by moving a file to its parent directory and then moving it back (56:30-58:06).
  • Refinement and Future Improvements (58:11): The speaker notes that the command could be further refined by adding error checking for root directories and printing messages about the move (58:11).
  • He also discusses simplifying the code by removing unnecessary variables (59:23) and functional programing technique to not use any variable or constant.

  Notes at
  http ://xahlee .info/talk_show/xah_talk_show_ep712.html
  Copy the link, remove spaces, paste the link in browser tab.
  Google Chrome and Firefox browsers censor websites by auto adding s in http and says the site Secure Connection Failed.
  Use Brave Browser or Safari.</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:25:11 +0000</pubDate><category>elisp</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Golang in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p_xX_vX8M7g</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p_xX_vX8M7g</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p_xX_vX8M7g">youtube</a><br><br>LSP support, linting, formatting, debugging, reading docs, version control.

  ,# Slides and conf
  - https://github.com/skybert/skybert-talks/blob/main/emacs-go-setup/emacs-go.org
  - https://gitlab.com/skybert/my-little-friends/-/blob/master/emacs/

  ,# Connect
  🕸️ https://skybert.net
  🐘 https://hachyderm.io/@skybert
  📫 torstein@skybert.net</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 17:21:58 +0000</pubDate><category>golang</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Xah Talk Show Ep710 Emacs Lisp Coding, lookup grokipedia, goto line in next pane</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UQC8Rav5zic</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UQC8Rav5zic</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UQC8Rav5zic">youtube</a><br><br>Video Summary (Generated by AI, Reviewed by Human.)

      This video is an Emacs Lisp coding session focused on creating and fixing two commands: lookup-grokipedia and go-to-char/go-to-line.
      The speaker begins by demonstrating the go-to-line command, which allows users to jump to a specific line number in another pane (0:37).
      He then introduces Grokipedia, a new encyclopedia by Elon Musk, explaining that it aims to provide a different perspective on "power-sensitive" topics compared to Wikipedia, which the speaker claims contains "fake news" on such subjects (11:12).
      He demonstrates this by comparing Wikipedia and Grokipedia entries for "Gamergate" (16:15).
      The speaker also mentions that for non-political topics like programming or mathematics, Grokipedia currently offers plain text versions of Wikipedia articles without illustrations or interlinks (21:06).
      He then proceeds to code the lookup-grokipedia command in Emacs Lisp, demonstrating how to grab the current word under the cursor and construct a URL to search Grokipedia (25:02).
      Finally, the speaker fixes a bug in his go-to-line command (32:02) and briefly discusses his use of multiple web browsers (35:16) and his Emacs Lisp packages, including Xah Fly Keys (2:51) and "Xah Emacs Lisp Mode" (39:18).

  Notes at
  http ://xahlee .info/talk_show/xah_talk_show_ep710.html
  Copy the link, remove spaces, paste the link in browser tab.
  Google Chrome and Firefox browsers censor websites by auto adding s in http and says the site Secure Connection Failed.
  Use Brave Browser or Safari.</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 08:58:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs For Writers Unit 9: Installing Packages</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZKesc3eFcxY</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZKesc3eFcxY</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZKesc3eFcxY">youtube</a><br><br>Emacs users have access to a wide network of installable packages.  These packages can be used to extend the base functionality of Emacs, so you can save time, do more, and have fun.

  EMACS FOR WRITERS HANDBOOK:
  https://chris-maiorana.kit.com/products/emacs-for-writers

  chrismaiorana.com</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 19:45:51 +0000</pubDate><category>configuration</category>
<category>packages</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>emacs literate org mode config for your init.el</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qn6PnM2nNy0</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qn6PnM2nNy0</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qn6PnM2nNy0">youtube</a><br><br>instead of having one big emacs init.el you can split the file up into code blocks each under their own heading in an org file and then tangle or write out all the code blocks to a file

  inj this video i show you how to use org demarcate block to split a code block into multiple new blocks which can be filed under their own headings

  we then use noweb-ref in a org properties drawer to apply a name to all the code blocks under a subtree which can then be tangled using another source code block that references those blocks

  the advantage of this method is that you can tangle the code blocks to multiple locations instead of tangling the entire document

  nixos dotfiles
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles/blob/master/nixos-dotfiles.org

  changelog
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/changelog

  org demarcate block
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/cerberus/blob/master/emacs/org-demarcate-block.org</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 17:48:17 +0000</pubDate><category>org</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eldoc-mouse demo for emacs lisp</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NO8818bzwmU</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NO8818bzwmU</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NO8818bzwmU">youtube</a><br><br>Demo for display documentation for variable and functions for mouse hover using package Eldoc-mouse
  https://github.com/huangfeiyu/eldoc-mouse</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 13:22:48 +0000</pubDate><category>EldocMouse</category>
<category>eldoc</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs is my COMPUTER now...</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n5VMWuxLi10</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n5VMWuxLi10</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n5VMWuxLi10">youtube</a><br><br>I am using emacs as my computer now. Check out the original blogpost: https://joshblais.com/blog/how-i-am-deeply-integrating-emacs/
  and HackerNews discussion: https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45832341

  Come join me on IRC or XMPP: https://joshblais.com/community

  libera.chat - #technicalrenaissance

  NixOS Configuration & Dotfiles: https://github.com/jblais493/nixos-config

  My Setup:
  Thinkpad t14s Gen 3 - https://amzn.to/3WxfOwi
  Majexstand - https://amzn.to/3ydquZd
  Chocofi Keyboard - https://shop.beekeeb.com/product/presoldered-chocofi-split-keyboard/
  Ulanzi Superclamp - https://amzn.to/3SwVv12
  Logitech MX Ergo - https://amzn.to/4dqzetJ
  Shure SM7B - https://amzn.to/3LMzMyr
  Audient ID4 Mkii - https://amzn.to/3Sz9e7A
  Anker 100w GaN Charger - https://amzn.to/3LKH99A
  Cables - https://amzn.to/3WvIjdX
  Moondrop Kato - https://amzn.to/46xsUyd
  Ulanzi Tripod - https://amzn.to/4cc3szN

  My website: https://joshblais.com
  My Book: https://mountainthebook.com
  Github: https://github.com/jblais493/
  Twitter: https://twitter.com/realjoshuablais
  Instagra: https://instagram.com/joshuablais

  If you enjoy my content, please consider tipping at any of the following support channels:

  Buy Me a Coffee: https://buymeacoffee.com/joshuablais
  Ko-fi: https://ko-fi.com/joshuablais
  LiberaPay: https://liberapay.com/joshuablais/
  Github Sponsors: https://github.com/sponsors/jblais493</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 18:41:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meanwhile on Emacs life...</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/shorts/3bo4ZNUoGqs</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/shorts/3bo4ZNUoGqs</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/3bo4ZNUoGqs">youtube</a><br><br></div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:10:08 +0000</pubDate><category>fun</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bending Emacs - Episode 05: Ready Player Mode</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BjCgo6NC9Zw</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BjCgo6NC9Zw</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BjCgo6NC9Zw">youtube</a><br><br>In this episode, we look at Ready Player Mode for music playback

  Notes from the video at https://xenodium.com/bending-emacs-episode-5-ready-player-mode

  Also of interest:

  - A Tour of Ready Player Mode: https://xenodium.com/a-tour-of-ready-player-mode
  - The Dired Abstraction: https://xenodium.com/the-dired-abstraction</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 12:20:24 +0000</pubDate><category>music</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why I Use Emacs for Ontologies (and How to Memorize a HUGE Knowledge Graph) [AMA #1]</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R6gYZ5B4lqs</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R6gYZ5B4lqs</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R6gYZ5B4lqs">youtube</a><br><br>Why would an Ontology Engineer skip tools like Protege and TopBraid Composer and stick with a 'plain' text editor like Emacs? And how do you manage a complex knowledge graph with thousands of classes and properties without relying on memory alone? Those were two great questions from FredBlok4308, and I'm answering them in this video.

  I dive into my personal workflow, explaining the history and practical reasons for choosing a text-based approach (hint: it's a historical happy accident that was supported by it being fun, fully customizable, and better than the other options I tried). I also reveal the secret to taming graph complexity, which involves good modular design, the "use it or lose it" principle, and leveraging SPARQL queries to serve as your method for learning the vocabula. Whether you're a Semantic Web veteran or just starting with knowledge graphs, this covers the critical strategies for scaling your data modeling efforts.</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 13:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Easy Setup for Drew Adams&apos; Essential Emacs Packages on Emacswiki</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EVjJMssj5iA</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EVjJMssj5iA</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EVjJMssj5iA">youtube</a><br><br>Learn how to automatically download and configure 39 powerful Emacs packages from Drew Adams, including Icicles (interactive completion), Bookmark+, Dired+, and more. This video shows you:

  - How to use the automated download script
  - Where packages are installed (~/.emacs.d/wiki/)
  - Basic Emacs configuration to get started
  - Command-line options for the script

  https://github.com/emacselements/emacswiki-packages

  My website: https://emacselements.com/</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 02:40:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Never stop writing in Emacs (productive transparency!)</title>
      <link>https://youtu.be/9_iYMas_mGo</link>
      <guid>https://youtu.be/9_iYMas_mGo</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://youtu.be/9_iYMas_mGo">youtube</a><br><br>A cool trick to impress writers.

  Productive transparency!!

  (Combined with all my previous tricks, Key Chords, rare bigrams, Braille Inspired, directional bindings, we achieve next level control  in writing!! Now we have a transparent Emacs client, instant and temporary!)

  Supporting me will inspire me to produce more quality content

  Show some support by buying me coffee on my Ko-fi page. It accepts your usual Debit/Credit card with 0% fee.
  https://ko-fi.com/ardiemejia83

  Or can donate straight to my PayPal
  https://paypal.me/ardiemejia83</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 02:00:09 +0000</pubDate><category>transparency</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quick Git Tip Using Magit Inside Emacs 2025_11_04_02:55:35</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1GVoHtZjGlw</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1GVoHtZjGlw</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1GVoHtZjGlw">youtube</a><br><br>In this video, you will see,

  ,#linux #linuxadmin #sysadmin #opensource #Gentoo #Debian #Slackware #research
  ,#linuxkernel #kernel #gnu #Linux #GNU #shorts

  Buy Me A Coffee: https://www.buymeacoffee.com/unixbhaskar
  Patreon: https://www.patreon.com/unixbhaskar
  Paypal: https://paypal.me/linuxbhaskar

  You can also find me :

  GitHub: https://github.com/unixbhaskar

  Reddit: https://www.reddit.com/user/unixbhaskar

  Blogs: https://unixbhaskar.wordpress.com

  Twitter: https://twitter.com/unixbhaskar

  Linkedin: https://linkedin.com/in/unixbhaskar

  Vimeo: https://vimeo.com/unixbhaskar

  Goodreads: https://goodreads.com/unixbhaskar</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 21:38:18 +0000</pubDate><category>magit</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs dired video thumbnails with ffmpegthumbnailer</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L2CUydP07ug</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L2CUydP07ug</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L2CUydP07ug">youtube</a><br><br>the emacs media-thumbnailer package uses ffmpegthumbnailer to show video thumbnails in dired and you can configure the thumbnail size and image cache location as well

  emacs dired media-thumbnailer
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/cerberus/blob/master/emacs/media-thumbnailer.org

  ffmpegthumbnailer
  https://github.com/dirkvdb/ffmpegthumbnailer

  media-thumbnailer
  https://github.com/jojojames/media-thumbnail

  nixos dotfiles
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 20:50:32 +0000</pubDate><category>dired</category>
<category>video</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs eglot and language servers for auto completion</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f7UX79i_mmc</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f7UX79i_mmc</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f7UX79i_mmc">youtube</a><br><br>Eglot is an Emacs package that works as an lcp client that connects to a language server to provide features like auto complete, go to definition, find all references etc.

  You can install language server for languages like bash, python and dozens more and then map a mode like python to the python lsp server, so whenever you open a python file it starts the python lsp server automatically

  lsp servers notes
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/cerberus/blob/master/emacs/lsp-servers.org

  emacs eglot
  https://github.com/joaotavora/eglot

  bash-language-server
  https://github.com/bash-lsp/bash-language-server

  python-lsp-server
  https://github.com/python-lsp/python-lsp-server

  nixd
  https://github.com/nix-community/nixd

  nixos emacs config
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles/tree/master/.config/emacs

  debian emacs config
  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/debian-dotfiles/tree/master/.config/emacs

  language server protocol
  https://microsoft.github.io/language-server-protocol/</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 18:56:20 +0000</pubDate><category>eglot</category>
<category>lsp</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Useful Templating System in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0qEHgiaSnsw</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0qEHgiaSnsw</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0qEHgiaSnsw">youtube</a><br><br>Let's see a package in Emacs, YASnippet, which offers a powerful templating system.

  Discover YASnippet:
  - https://github.com/joaotavora/yasnippet

  Support my effort :)
  - https://www.patreon.com/hexdump

  Learn Web Application Security:
  - https://www.udemy.com/course/practical-wapt/?referralCode=15450B3828BA5A3B23CB

  Learn Linux Privilege Escalation:
  - https://www.udemy.com/course/linux-privesc/?couponCode=33738F67D2C09EB25600

  Official Forum and Website:
  - https://forum.hexdump.sh
  - https://hexdump.sh

  TIMESTAMPS

  00:00 What is YASnippet?
  03:00 Installation
  05:00 Create a template
  08:00 Usage</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 12:17:30 +0000</pubDate><category>yasnippet</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs For Writers Unit 8: Your First Configuration</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6yLmEGIIwb0</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6yLmEGIIwb0</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6yLmEGIIwb0">youtube</a><br><br>In this video, we will look at how you can configure your Emacs install with the magic configuration file. The "config" holds your user preferences. It's coded with Emacs Lisp.  You don't have to be an expert in Elisp to get started. You can start with my "darkstar" config or piece together examples from the Internet.

  STARTER CONFIG:
  https://github.com/cryptstopher/darkstar

  EMACS FOR WRITERS HANDBOOK:
  https://chris-maiorana.kit.com/products/emacs-for-writers

  chrismaiorana.com</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 19:30:26 +0000</pubDate><category>configuration</category>
<category>beginner</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>buffer-restore.el - Save and Restore Emacs Window Layouts with Named Sessions</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kf68nibRKXc</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kf68nibRKXc</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kf68nibRKXc">youtube</a><br><br>https://github.com/emacselements/buffer-restore

  Quick demo of buffer-restore.el, an Emacs package for manual session management.

  Unlike desktop-save-mode, buffer-restore lets you save multiple named sessions and workspaces, giving you explicit control over when to save and restore your layouts.

  Key Features:
  • Save/restore single frame layouts (sessions)
  • Save/restore multiple frames with positions (workspaces)
  • Preserves exact PDF pages, EPUB chapters, and cursor positions
  • Perfect for switching between different work contexts

  Commands shown:
  - buffer-restore-save-session
  - buffer-restore-load-session
  - buffer-restore-save-workspace
  - buffer-restore-load-workspace

  ,#emacs #productivity #opensource #plato #republic</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 09:35:55 +0000</pubDate><category>navigation</category>
<category>BufferRestore</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hacking on Emacs #4: window configuration after magit commit</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R1Lo-wGZIVY</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R1Lo-wGZIVY</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R1Lo-wGZIVY">youtube</a><br><br>Making sure window configuration stays the same after finishing Magit commit (when using `current-window-only`)

  ► Main channel: https://www.youtube.com/@jakubkadlcik
  ► GitHub: https://github.com/FrostyX
  ► Blog: https://frostyx.cz
  ► Mastodon: https://fosstodon.org/@FrostyX</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 17:15:58 +0000</pubDate><category>configuration</category>
<category>window</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs For Writers Unit 7: Advanced Text Markup in Org Mode</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vNFnQz8iUF8</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vNFnQz8iUF8</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vNFnQz8iUF8">youtube</a><br><br>In this video, we go beyond the basics of italics, bold, and underline formatting to take look at some more advanced constructs in Org Mode, including an intro to structured blocks and export options.

  EMACS FOR WRITERS HANDBOOK:
  https://chris-maiorana.kit.com/products/emacs-for-writers

  chrismaiorana.com</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 19:39:44 +0000</pubDate><category>org</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GNU Emacs do Zero - Episódio 01</title>
      <link>https://youtu.be/jHTc2tiXt8M</link>
      <guid>https://youtu.be/jHTc2tiXt8M</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://youtu.be/jHTc2tiXt8M">youtube</a><br><br>Neste vídeo vamos aprender o básico do Emacs e já introduzir ao Org-mode.

  ,#emacs #gnuemacs #gnu #development #developer #editor</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 16:03:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>أساسيات إيماكس كمحرر نصوص | The Basics of Emacs as a Text Editor</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tBwu127eVyk</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tBwu127eVyk</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tBwu127eVyk">youtube</a><br><br>دعم القناة:
  إذا أعجبك المحتوى وترغب في دعم عملي، يمكنك شراء قهوة لي من هنا:
  ☕ https://buymeacoffee.com/the.omania

  دوراتنا في لينكس وتقنية المعلومات:
  https://omanialearninghub.com

  انضم إلى مجموعة فيسبوك للشبكات وتقنية المعلومات:
  https://www.facebook.com/groups/omanialearninghub/

  انضم إلى مجموعة التليقرام للشبكات وتقنية المعلومات:
  https://t.me/OmaniaLearningHub

  تابعني على تيك توك:
  https://www.tiktok.com/@the.omania

  أضفني على سناب شات:
  https://www.snapchat.com/add/the.omania دعم القناة:</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 08:42:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>show doc for candidate of complete of company/corfu in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://youtube.com/watch?v=6B45y7lU9Zw&amp;si=JcFtMhc2y9AhTLV8</link>
      <guid>https://youtube.com/watch?v=6B45y7lU9Zw&amp;si=JcFtMhc2y9AhTLV8</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=6B45y7lU9Zw&si=JcFtMhc2y9AhTLV8">youtube</a><br><br>I just learned that we can show the document for the candidate as we move through the candidates list of company/corfu.
  For company, it requires either of the following packages to show document for candidate
  1. https://github.com/company-mode/company-quickhelp or
  2. https://github.com/sebastiencs/company-box
  For Corfu, not additional package is needed. just add (corfu-popupinfo-mode) in "init"
  (use-package corfu
    :custom
    (corfu-cycle t)
    (corfu-preview-current nil)
    :init
    (global-corfu-mode)
    (corfu-popupinfo-mode) ;; this is for show document for candidate
    )</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 06:41:28 +0000</pubDate><category>company</category>
<category>corfu</category>
<category>completion</category>
<category>elisp</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hacking on Emacs #2: Enabling forge.fedoraproject.org support for git-link</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XkgymMFV1HQ</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XkgymMFV1HQ</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XkgymMFV1HQ">youtube</a><br><br>► Main channel: https://www.youtube.com/@jakubkadlcik
  ► GitHub: https://github.com/FrostyX
  ► Blog: https://frostyx.cz
  ► Mastodon: https://fosstodon.org/@FrostyX</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 13:05:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs and json-par-mode to navigate through records in a JSON file</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WDVCmJNDhDw</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WDVCmJNDhDw</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WDVCmJNDhDw">youtube</a><br><br>There are many applications that can help you browsing relatively complex JSON files. Emacs is one of a powerful choice.</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 10:37:44 +0000</pubDate><category>json</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piping in and out of Emacs buffers.</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LVlF3-KyqvY</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LVlF3-KyqvY</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LVlF3-KyqvY">youtube</a><br><br>Let's pipe some content in and out of Emacs in terminal.

  It's a brief demo of https://github.com/agzam/mx-piper</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 03:19:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&quot;It Works&quot;: More Adventures with Racket and Emacs</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OJqocEYhgng</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OJqocEYhgng</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OJqocEYhgng">youtube</a><br><br>Greg Hendershott
  "It Works": More Adventures with Racket and Emacs
  The Emacs package "racket-mode" has continued to evolve its design and features. Among other things, it allows multiple local and remote back ends, has a redesigned "lossless" REPL, supports modern Emacs UI completion annotations, and enables lang-driven editing. Most recently the step debugger has gotten some attention.
  Bio: Greg Hendershott has a useless degree in philosophy, a background in the music software industry, and a decade working in the open source Racket and Emacs communities. Tedious details are available at greghendershott.com.</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 19:03:42 +0000</pubDate><category>racket</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Treesitter &quot;show definition&quot; in C with Emacs</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IEGfWHOg_GQ</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IEGfWHOg_GQ</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IEGfWHOg_GQ">youtube</a><br><br>I have given up on  the complexity of LSPs, I just use the _amazing_ treesitter library instead: parsing my code as I type it's very fast and can do nearly everything that an LSP can do but this way I just have to deal with programming Emacs, which is super easy.

  I've got this on the Internet over here:
  https://tangled.org/@nicferrier.bsky.social/nic-emacs-treesitter-stuff

  There's a readme which makes an attempt to explain how to try and use it but it's still very much a work in progress.

  My main focus is C, because that's what I'm programming in mostly. So if you're a C programmer and an Emacs user and you want to try it - then download it from tangled and give mea shout if it doesn't work.</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 11:36:18 +0000</pubDate><category>TreeSitter</category>
<category>coding</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs gptel and mcp-searxng enable web search for your llm&apos;s with searxng</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6xv28WTiGsI</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6xv28WTiGsI</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6xv28WTiGsI">youtube</a><br><br>The emacs gptel package lets you use local llm's with ollama as well as online llm's like Gemini
  however the issue is the models dont have web access so they have a cut off in their knowledge based on when they were built

  Installing the mcp.el package with gptel provides the mcp protocol to work with mcp servers
  this allows us to use the mcp-searxng server that works with the searxng self hosted search engine to enable web searches for our llm's

  The mcp-searxng server also lets you download web pages as well

  The mcp-nixos server allows us to search for nixos packages from within Emacs,
  as well other tools to show the latest channel and other useful stuff

  The mcp.el package works with models that support tools using ollama like llama3.1
  or with online models like Gemini

  docker.el lets you manage your podman or docker container from within Emacs,
  and the dockerfile-mode package provides syntax highlighting for Dockerfiles

  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/cerberus/blob/master/emacs/gptel-mcp-severs.org

  https://github.com/karthink/gptel?tab=readme-ov-file#model-context-protocol-mcp-integration

  https://github.com/lizqwerscott/mcp.el

  https://github.com/Silex/docker.el

  https://github.com/spotify/dockerfile-mode

  https://github.com/ihor-sokoliuk/mcp-searxng

  https://github.com/utensils/mcp-nixos

  Seaxng search engine podman install
  https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qAKmxK6juwI

  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/cerberus/blob/master/searxng/searxng-podman.org

  https://github.com/NapoleonWils0n/nixos-dotfiles</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 22:30:56 +0000</pubDate><category>ai</category>
<category>gptel</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bending Emacs - Episode 4: Batch renaming files</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1E0ThCSr8Qw</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1E0ThCSr8Qw</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1E0ThCSr8Qw">youtube</a><br><br>In this video I show a handful of ways to batch rename files. Primarily based around Emacs dired, mulitple cursors, and keyboard macros. Written notes available at blog post https://lmno.lol/alvaro/bending-emacs-episode-4-batch-renaming-files</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 16:35:28 +0000</pubDate><category>dired</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs For Writers Unit 6: Welcome to Org Mode</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YzO2HjhLYBk</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YzO2HjhLYBk</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YzO2HjhLYBk">youtube</a><br><br>In this video, you will finally get a glimpse of Org Mode, the mode that's more than a mode. It's a whole productivity suite, but even if you don't use the productivity tools, it's a powerful way to organize and compose rich outlines and beautifully written documents.  All the while, you can be cool while doing it.  Check it out.

  EMACS FOR WRITERS HANDBOOK:
  https://chris-maiorana.kit.com/products/emacs-for-writers

  VIDEO ON INSTALL ORG CONTRIB PACKAGE INSTALLATION:
  https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FW8CkvZtNgY

  chrismaiorana.com</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 16:59:18 +0000</pubDate><category>org</category>
<category>writing</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fulltext, semantic text and image search in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t879-fipgtg</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t879-fipgtg</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t879-fipgtg">youtube</a><br><br>I show my new org-db package for full and semantic text and image search in Emacs. This package indexes your org-files and provides several ways to search them by org-heading, full text with fts5 in sqlite, vector search for semantic search, and searching images from textual descriptions using CLIP!

  The whole project was "vibe-coded" with Claude Code over about 7 days. It is still in an alpha stage of development, but I have been using it for a few days now, and am pretty happy with it.

  https://github.com/jkitchin/org-db-v3</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 13:18:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs as a Microsoft Word killer part 3</title>
      <link>https://youtu.be/1kUqgYk_rrI</link>
      <guid>https://youtu.be/1kUqgYk_rrI</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://youtu.be/1kUqgYk_rrI">youtube</a><br><br>Emacs as Microsoft Word killer part 3

  Using Conditionals and Defvar to Simplify Multiple Configs Across Multiple Platforms.

  Supporting me will inspire me to produce more quality content

  Show some support by buying me coffee on my Ko-fi page. It accepts your usual Debit/Credit card with 0% fee.
  https://ko-fi.com/ardiemejia83

  Or can donate straight to my PayPal
  https://paypal.me/ardiemejia83</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 01:00:04 +0000</pubDate><category>configuration</category>
<category>elisp</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emacs For Writers Unit 5: Basic File Management and Navigation</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rhjBvrENwVY</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rhjBvrENwVY</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rhjBvrENwVY">youtube</a><br><br>In this video, we will cover basic file management with the directory editor in Emacs, also known as "Dired," as well as some rudimentary buffer navigation.

  EMACS FOR WRITERS HANDBOOK:
  https://chris-maiorana.kit.com/products/emacs-for-writers

  chrismaiorana.com</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 22:49:27 +0000</pubDate><category>dired</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Showcasing Some of My Essential Emacs and Shell Tools on GitHub</title>
      <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8P4T5Pr36v8</link>
      <guid>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8P4T5Pr36v8</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<div id="content"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8P4T5Pr36v8">youtube</a><br><br>https://github.com/emacselements

  In this video, I walk through my personal collection of GitHub repositories, each designed to streamline and enhance your Emacs experience or automate daily tasks. The repo also some interesting Shell Scripts and  Python Apps, notably: Redactor, Video-Sorter, and Image-Viewer.</div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 14:41:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>